<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter id="advanced-topics" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude">
  <title>Advanced Topics</title>

  <refsect2 id="compatibility">
    <title>Device and print compatibility</title>

    <para>
    Moving off generic conceptual ideas and onto libfprint-specific
    implementation details, here are some introductory notes regarding how
    libfprint copes with compatibility of fingerprints.
    </para>

    <para>
    libfprint deals with a whole variety of different fingerprint readers and
    the design includes considerations of compatibility and interoperability
    between multiple devices. Your application should also be prepared to
    work with more than one type of fingerprint reader and should consider that
    enrolled fingerprint X may not be compatible with the device the user has
    plugged in today.
    </para>

    <para>
    libfprint implements the principle that fingerprints from different devices
    are not necessarily compatible. For example, different devices may see
    significantly different areas of fingerprint surface, and comparing images
    between the devices would be unreliable. Also, devices can stretch and
    distort images in different ways.
    </para>

    <para>
    libfprint also implements the principle that in some cases, fingerprints
    <emphasis>are</emphasis> compatible between different devices. If you go and buy two
    identical fingerprint readers, it seems logical that you should be able
    to enroll on one and verify on another without problems.
    </para>

    <para>
    libfprint takes a fairly simplistic approach to these issues. Internally,
    fingerprint hardware is driven by individual drivers. libfprint enforces
    that a fingerprint that came from a device backed by driver X is never
    compared to a fingerprint that came from a device backed by driver Y.
    </para>

    <para>
    Additionally, libfprint is designed for the situation where a single driver
    may support a range of devices which differ in imaging or scanning
    properties. For example, a driver may support two ranges of devices which
    even though are programmed over the same interface, one device sees
    substantially less of the finger flesh, therefore images from the two
    device types should be incompatible despite being from the same driver. To
    implement this, each driver assigns a <emphasis>device type</emphasis> to each device
    that it detects based on its imaging characteristics. libfprint ensures that
    two prints being compared have the same device type.
    </para>

    <para>
    In summary, libfprint represents fingerprints in several internal structures
    and each representation will offer you a way of determining the
    <ulink url="#driver_id">driver ID</ulink> and <ulink url="#device-types">devtype</ulink> of the print in
    question. Prints are only compatible if the driver ID <emphasis role="strong">and</emphasis> devtypes
    match. libfprint does offer you some "is this print compatible?" helper
    functions, so you don't have to worry about these details too much.
    </para>
  </refsect2>

  <refsect2 id="driver_id">
    <title>Driver IDs</title>

    <para>
    Each driver is assigned a unique ID by the project maintainer. These
    assignments are
    <ulink url="https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/libfprint/libfprint/blob/master/libfprint/drivers/driver_ids.h">
    documented in the sources</ulink> and will never change.
    </para>

    <para>
    The only reason you may be interested in retrieving the driver ID for a
    driver is for the purpose of checking if some print data is compatible
    with a device. libfprint uses the driver ID as one way of checking that
    the print you are trying to verify is compatible with the device in
    question - it ensures that enrollment data from one driver is never fed to
    another. Note that libfprint does provide you with helper functions to
    determine whether a print is compatible with a device, so under most
    circumstances, you don't have to worry about driver IDs at all.
    </para>
  </refsect2>

  <refsect2 id="device-types">
    <title>Device types</title>

    <para>
    Internally, the <ulink url="libfprint-Driver-operations.html#libfprint-Driver-operations.description">driver</ulink> behind a device assigns a 32-bit
    <emphasis>devtype</emphasis> identifier to the device. This cannot be used as a unique
    ID for a specific device as many devices under the same range may share
    the same devtype. The devtype may even be 0 in all cases.
    </para>

    <para>
    The only reason you may be interested in retrieving the devtype for a
    device is for the purpose of checking if some print data is compatible
    with a device. libfprint uses the devtype as one way of checking that the
    print you are verifying is compatible with the device in question - the
    devtypes must be equal. This effectively allows drivers to support more
    than one type of device where the data from each one is not compatible with
    the other. Note that libfprint does provide you with helper functions to
    determine whether a print is compatible with a device, so under most
    circumstances, you don't have to worry about devtypes at all.
    </para>
  </refsect2>

</chapter>
